<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true account of the passages at Mergen in the kingdom of Syam after Captain Anthony Weltden arrived at that port in the Curtana frigat, for account of the East India Company / humbly presented to the honourable the knights, citizens, and burgesses in Parliament assembled, by Samuel White.</title>
            <author>White, Samuel, ca. 1650-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65771</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1805A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38308</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17290990</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17290990</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106340</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65771)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106340)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1163:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true account of the passages at Mergen in the kingdom of Syam after Captain Anthony Weltden arrived at that port in the Curtana frigat, for account of the East India Company / humbly presented to the honourable the knights, citizens, and burgesses in Parliament assembled, by Samuel White.</title>
                  <author>White, Samuel, ca. 1650-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: creased, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>East India Company.</term>
               <term>British --  Thailand.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106340:1"/>
            <head>A True ACCOUNT OF THE Paſſages at MERGEN IN THE KINGDOM of <hi>SYAM,</hi> After Captain <hi>Anthony Weltden</hi> arrived at that <hi>Port</hi> in the <hi>Curtana Frigat,</hi> for Account of the EAST-INDIA Company.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Humbly Preſented</hi> To the Honourable the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes in Parliament Aſſembled: By <hi>Samuel White.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the State of my Caſe, repreſenting the inſupportable Grievances I at preſent labour under by the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Companies unjuſt and arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Practices I had occaſion to intimate that <hi>His Majeſty</hi> of <hi>Syam,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on notice that the ſaid Companies Servants had committed Hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties againſt him by ſeizing his Ships, was reſolved to appeal to our <hi>Sovereign Lord</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and make <hi>His Majeſty</hi> the ſole Arbitrator of all Matters depending 'twixt him and the ſaid Company. For which Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he was pleas'd to command my Service, and order'd me to prepare a Ship of my own for the Voyage, as I accordingly did, and only waited for my diſpatches from <hi>Court;</hi> When on the 26th of <hi>June,</hi> 87. Captain <hi>Weltden</hi> in the <hi>Curtana,</hi> and ſoon after Captain <hi>Goſtlin</hi> in the <hi>Sloop James</hi> came into the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Mergen</hi> under <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Colours, and when I had very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectfully receiv'd Captain <hi>Weltden</hi> at his Landing, he requir'd me in the Name of <hi>Our Sovereign Lord the King</hi> to ſummon all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> on the Place, that he might Publiſh <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Commands to them, as was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly done, and after he had read the <hi>Proclamation,</hi> together with a Paper from the <hi>Preſident</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> he demanded whether they were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to give due Obedience to their <hi>Sovereign</hi>'s Orders in leaving the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Syam</hi>'s Service, and return with him to <hi>Fort</hi> St. <hi>George,</hi> whereto 'twas una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly anſwer'd, <hi>Yes,</hi> and <hi>God Save the King,</hi> after which ſatisfactory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106340:2"/>he told them he came not to injure any of them, but to protect their Plerſons and Eſtates, and that they might pay themſelves any Arrears of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by Plunder on the <hi>King of Syam,</hi> or his Subjects Goods. At the hearing whereof, I thought it next to my Allegiance to my <hi>Native Sovereign,</hi> a moſt incumbent Duty on me to that <hi>Prince</hi> I had the Honour to ſerve in ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a Charge, to tell them, It much rejoyced me to find they all agreed in a Loyal Obedience to the Command of the <hi>King Our Lord;</hi> and to put them into better Circumſtances for a preſent Compliance, without any ſuch acts of Violence as was intimated by the Captain, I was ready to pay eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man what Wages was due to that very day, as I accordingly did, and declar'd them at that time diſcharg'd from the <hi>King of Syam</hi>'s Service.</p>
            <p>After this, the Captain had a Conference with thoſe <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> on the Place, that were <hi>Native Syamers,</hi> to whom he delivered a Letter from the <hi>Preſident</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> injoyning them to forward one that accompanied it to the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Syam;</hi> the Import whereof was to demand ſatisfaction for Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries alledged to be done to the Company and their Dependents, to amount of about 65000 <hi>l.</hi> and to acquaint him that they had ſent this Ship to block up that <hi>Port,</hi> with order to await ſixty days for an Anſwer, and in failure of compliance in that time, to proceed to make themſelves Reparation by force of their Arms.</p>
            <p>As to my ſelf, the Captain was pleas'd to tell me he had order to expect thirty days for my Anſwer; but I was better reſolv'd than to need any time to conſider whether I would obey <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Command, and accordingly I did without delay declare my mind to him in Writing: But as to the Mandate from the <hi>Preſident</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> wherein they did by their own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority impoſe on me to take up Arms againſt the <hi>King of Syam,</hi> I could not but proteſt againſt it, nor can I now mention it without avowing a juſt Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of ſo nefarious an Act as it would have been in me, to draw a Sword againſt my Royal and bountiful <hi>Maſter,</hi> to whoſe <hi>Princely</hi> Benignity I ſtand ſo highly oblig'd, that all the Services of my Life can never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge me, and therefore I hope I ſhould rather embrace the moſt cruel Death, than be induc'd to any thing may juſtly render me ungrateful.</p>
            <p>ALL things did to this time look as well as was poſſible under ſo ſtrange a Conjuncture, there paſſing daily intercourſes of Friendſhip betwixt the Captain and Us of the Shore, and he declaring himſelf very well pleas'd with his kind Reception by the <hi>Syam Magiſtrates,</hi> and the care was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to tranſlate and forward his diſpatches to <hi>Court;</hi> ſo that there was not any cauſe to doubt but this Tranquillity would at leaſt continue till the ſixty days limited for the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Syam</hi>'s Anſwer were expired. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on the fifth of <hi>July</hi> I went to <hi>Tenaſſary,</hi> a Town about fifty Miles diſtant, to tranſact ſome Affairs of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Syam</hi>'s that were under my care, but I had not been there two days before I was alarm'd by Letters from <hi>Mergen,</hi> acquainting me that the face of Affairs had on a ſudden, put on a very ill Aſpect, for that the Captain had actually made an Aſſault on the <hi>Port,</hi> in breaking up the Piles that were plac'd for its defence, and ſeiz'd two Boats the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> employ'd to await for the Ships expected from abroad, and alſo remov'd my foreſaid Ship that was fitted for the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Syam</hi>'s Service to <hi>England,</hi> carrying her from her moorings under command of his own Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat. Which ſurprizing Hoſtilities had ſo incens'd the People, that no <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhman</hi>'s Life could be ſuppos'd ſecure amongſt them; wherefore it concern'd me, as I regarded my own ſafety, to diſpeed my return, as I according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did, and arriv'd at <hi>Mergen</hi> the ſixth day after my departure, being the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106340:2"/>11th of <hi>July.</hi> Nor was I ſooner there than divers of our Nation came to give me a more particular Account of theſe unhappy Paſſages in my abſence, and were preſently follow'd by the <hi>Syam Magiſtrates,</hi> exclaiming againſt theſe Outrages with moſt paſſionate reſentments; demanding of me what could induce the Captain thus to violate his Faith ſo ſolemnly and publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engag'd to them, in declaring that he would await ſixty days for Anſwer to his pretended demands at <hi>Court;</hi> and now in this manner to break in upon them before a quarter of the time was expir'd. I had only to anſwer, That they well knew I was abſent on the <hi>King</hi>'s Service at <hi>Tenaſſary,</hi> whence this ill News had recall'd me ſome days ſooner than intended, ſo that I was under as great a Conſternation as themſelves poſſibly could be at theſe ſtrange Proceedings; but I had notice the Captain was now coming a Shore, from whom I would fully inform my ſelf, and communicate to them the truth of what I underſtood concerning it, which they told me they ſhould with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience expect, and ſo with a more than ordinary Fervency, injoyning me to manage my ſelf in this Affair as my Duty to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> the King of <hi>Syam</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd me, they withdrew with much ſeeming diſcontent and concern'dneſs. Some hours after, Captain <hi>Weltden</hi> came to my Houſe, whom I preſently accoſted as the occaſion requir'd, telling him how much I was aſtoniſh'd at the ſudden change of things in my few days abſence; And firſt I tax'd him with the affront and injury done to the <hi>Government</hi> of the Place, wherein he had forfeited his Obligation to them, which he voluntarily enter'd into by his own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, and I fear'd ſo unaccountable an Action might be of pernicious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence. For what dependence could we have on their ſincerity, when we had led them into the breach of Faith by our Example? And then as to what more particularly related to my ſelf in his entering my Ship with armed Men, and carrying her under Command of his own, I urg'd to him, That ſuch Violences did no way accord with his Declaration at his arrival, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he aſſur'd Us he came not to moleſt or injure any of Us, either in our Perſons or Eſtates, but to protect and aſſiſt Us in all things, as I according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confided. But now I found much cauſe to doubt that I was not ſecure in any thing, wherefore I deſir'd him to let me know the meaning of what he had already done, and what I was to expect for the future? Whereto the Captain was pleas'd to anſwer, That I need not trouble my ſelf ſo much in this matter, for nothing had been nor ſhould be done with deſign of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to my ſelf or any <hi>Engliſhman</hi> on the Place, but only for his own ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, which he muſt not be wanting to endeavour; and as to my Ship ſhe was ſafe, and not leſs at my command than when ſhe rid before my own door; the occaſion of his removing her being upon ſome intimations he had receiv'd, that he ſhould be deny'd any more Proviſions from the Shore, and hearing my Ship had good ſtore aboard for her intended Voyage to <hi>Europe,</hi> he brought her under command of his own for a Recruit in caſe of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. I reply'd, That I was very ſorry he was ſo eaſily inclin'd to credit ſuch falſe and groundleſs Suggeſtions, ſince he had not only my repeated Promiſes, that nothing the Place could afford ſhould be wanting to him, but had alſo experimented my correſponding Performances in larger ſupplies than his oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions had hitherto requir'd; which he readily and thankfully acknowledg'd, and added, that what was done was <hi>Irrevocably</hi> paſt, but re-aſſur'd me I ſhould not be a Sufferer in any thing.</p>
            <p>As to his drawing up the Piles that were plac'd for the defence of the Port he had little to ſay, onely that in regard they were not finiſh'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his arrival, he look'd upon it to be againſt the Law of Arms for them to go on fortifying in that time he had limited for a Ceſſation.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106340:3"/>
            <p>And as to his ſending his People to ſeize the Boats and Men the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates</hi> had employ'd to await without the <hi>Port,</hi> to give advices to the Ships expected from abroad, he would have juſtify'd it by a Reflection on me, ſaying he was certify'd I was inſtrumental, or at leaſt had ſome Cognizance of that matter, and he took it more ill becauſe he had formerly in occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Diſcourſe, aſſur'd me that whatever ſhould arrive on any bottom, that appear'd to belong to me or any <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> ſhould be duly deliver'd to the Proprietor. I anſwer'd him, That as I never doubted his Promiſe in that regard, ſo neither could I have any fears of the contrary; for how great ſoever the Priviledges were, which the <hi>Companies</hi> potent Influences at <hi>Court</hi> may have prevail'd to obtain of his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> I was heartily ſatisfy'd that <hi>Our Gracious Sovereign</hi> would not give them a Power to deſtroy and ruine their fellow Subjects, that were in all things obedient to his <hi>Royal</hi> Commands, as he had found my ſelf and all with me; wherefore it was no good <hi>Logick</hi> for him to infer from his foreſaid Promiſe, that I was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to betray my Truſt, in diſcovering what my Superiors had caus'd to be done in the Affairs of that <hi>Prince</hi> I had the honour and happineſs to ſerve many years; and might, I hop'd, without any ſtain to my Allegiance to my <hi>Native Sovereign</hi> continue ſo to do, till War was actually declar'd againſt him; Or that in that interim I receiv'd order to ſurrender up my Charge and Commiſſion to a Succeſſor in my Office. Which was the ſum of our Conference at this time, The Captain and his Company being pleaſed to ſtay with me till about nine at Night, and then returned aboard his Ship.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> 12th. Early this Morning the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> were again with me, to know what the Captain had offer'd in Juſtification of his ſtrange Actions; to whom I told the real Truth of all that paſs'd betwixt us, which did ſtill further incenſe them, urging, that if he had not better pretences for what was already done, they had reaſon to fear worſe afterwards. For what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority could his coming there with the Companies unreaſonable and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs demands give him to interrupt their buſineſs in the <hi>King</hi>'s Service? And to ſeize a Ship in <hi>Port,</hi> to whomſoever ſhe belonged, was yet as much to the <hi>King</hi>'s Diſhonor, as if it had been his own. I endeavour'd to palliate the matter as well as I could, and perſwade them to believe the Captain would offer them no further <hi>Prejudice,</hi> but await the remainer of the limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time for an Anſwer from <hi>Court.</hi> And here I enquir'd what was the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Fleet of Gallies that I ſaw yeſterday and to day in the River full man'd? They readily told me, it was to prevent the like which had happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for the future, and ſoon after parted in a great Diſguſt.</p>
            <p>In the Afternoon the Captain came again aſhore and gave me a Viſit, and at his return aboard in the Evening, when he came to the Waters ſide he obſerv'd the pre-mention'd Gallies to move croſs the River, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſent his <hi>Lieutenant</hi> to me to enquire the reaſon, and declare he doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome deſign againſt him: Which I aſſur'd him I was wholly ignorant of, and for his further ſatisfaction offer'd my ſelf to accompany him till he was paſt whatſoever he could ſuppoſe had any appearance of danger; as I accordingly did, and afterwards at his earneſt invitation proceeded with him on board his Ship, where I remained till next day Afternoon, and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to my Houſe, in which interim I found all had continued very quiet, and no news of any further motion by the <hi>Magiſtrates:</hi> which gave me hopes that what had paſs'd would have only awaken'd them to keep the ſtricter Guard, and make the beſt proviſion they could for their future De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. And becauſe the Captain had promis'd me he would give them no more ſuch Provocations, I flatter'd my ſelf into a pleaſing Opinion, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106340:3"/>we ſhould have been ſo far Friends again, as to have our Lives ſecure from any attempt, at leaſt till the ſixty days were accompliſh'd.</p>
            <p>But while I was thus dreaming of Safety, I found my ſelf and all my Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men on the brink of Deſtruction; For the very next day, being the 14th of <hi>July,</hi> the Captain, with ſeveral others, coming in the Afternoon to my Houſe, I detain'd them to Supper, and at the uſual hour, betwixt eight and nine of the Clock, he was for returning aboard, when all the Company waited on him to the outward Porch of my Houſe, but I accompany'd him about thirty foot further to the Waters ſide, where my Barge lay ready to receive him. And at the very moment of our parting, I was ſurpriz'd by a ſudden Blow with a great Club on the Sleeve of my Gown, and turning ſhort upon the Villain that ſtruck at me, he was ſo diſanimated, that he durſt not ſtay to repeat the ſtroke, but immediately fled from me; though I was deſtitute of any defence, being only in my Night-gown and Slippers, without Hat or Cap on my head. At the ſame inſtant the Captain was by a more unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Blow from another hand knock'd down, but in little time recover'd himſelf, though with the loſs of much Blood: and juſt as we were thus aſſaulted, I heard a hideous confuſed noiſe of a Multitude, which gave me a ſuſpicion they were at once aſſaſſinating all of our <hi>Nation,</hi> in which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal diſtreſs I firſt thought of retreating to my Houſe, where beſides ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen great Guns mounted on a Platform, I had ſtore of Ammunition and Arms of all ſorts within doors; but I no ſooner mov'd that way, than I diſcern'd a great company of armed Men, that were got between me and home, and ſo I had no other relief but to fly to my Barge, as I did, and preſently got her off, when I ſpy'd the Captain, and adventur'd to put aſhore again to take him in. The Guards which attended him being fourteen Men with a <hi>Lieutenant,</hi> in two Boats, made one diſcharge, and adventur'd to Land, where they were overpower'd, and all cut off, and ſo was every <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> (ſave four) with ſome of other Nations that were our Friends, as I was afterwards certify'd by a <hi>French</hi> Ship from that Place, before I left <hi>India.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Captain and I, having by a Miracle of Mercy made an Eſcape thus far, we made all the haſte we could to get aboard our Ships for further ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, and in our paſſage down I had the additional affliction of ſeeing my Houſe, Ware-houſes, and Ship-yard all in a Flame: nor were we with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Proſpect of encountering new Dangers; for as we proceeded towards our Ships, we had ſight of ſeveral <hi>Syam</hi> Boats, which were laid to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept any that ſhould eſcape from the Shore; and it was with much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty that we paſs'd by them undiſcover'd, till at laſt we arriv'd at the Place where the Ships rode the day before; but to our great Amazement they now appear'd not: Which after all former fears, caſt us quite into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, concluding ſome fatal Diſtaſter had alſo befallen them, and ſo depriv'd us of all poſſibility of ſaving our ſelves. However, that we might live as long as we could, we reſolv'd to make down with the Tide, which then happily favour'd us, to be farther from the Town at break of day. And under this doleful Conſternation, while we ſeem'd ſurrounded with Deaths on all ſides, having only to chooſe whether we would return to be kill'd, or proceed to be ſtarv'd or drown'd: As we row'd along we deſcry'd ſomething that loom'd like a Ship, which in two hours hard Rowing we came up with, and ſhe gave us new Life in proving to be my Ship <hi>Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> where we found Captain <hi>Goſtlin</hi> Commander of the <hi>Sloop James,</hi> with his Mate who eſcap'd in their Boat, and carry'd down the firſt ſad News of the <hi>Bloody Tragedy;</hi> upon which the <hi>Curtana</hi> and my Ship cut their Cables,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106340:4"/>and ſtood out over the <hi>Bar,</hi> where we happily got aboard about three of the Clock in the Morning, the <hi>Curtana</hi> being then about two Leagues from us, and ſtill under Sail, wherefore we fired our fore-Chaſe, as a ſign for them to Anchor, and about four of the Clock ſent a Boat for the Doctor to dreſs the Captains Wounds, who about ſeven was returned again with Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the Mates, that they ſhould bring the Ship nearer mine: but they were all ſo full of fear, that they took no notice of it, but as ſoon as the Tide preſented, they weigh'd and ſtood directly for the Channel, with the <hi>King</hi>'s Colours flying; and it was certainly the want of Wind, and not of good Will, that prevented their running away with the Ship, and gave the Captain opportunity of overtaking them in my Long-boat about ſeven at Night, at which time he got ſafely aboard the <hi>Curtana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS is a faithful Relation of all that paſſed under my Cognizance in this diſmal Cataſtrophe, wherein, by a miraculous Providence, I eſcap'd with my Life, but was at once depriv'd of a very conſiderable Eſtate I had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy acquir'd, and a fair Proſpect of a far greater addition to it: And what ought not to be a leſs trouble to my Mind, is, that by means of theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable proceedings at <hi>Mergen,</hi> I have loſt my <hi>Intereſt</hi> in the Favour of one of the beſt <hi>Princes</hi> in the World, and lie at preſent under the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved cenſure of having been treacherous to his <hi>Intereſt,</hi> by whoſe <hi>Gracious Indulgence</hi> I was advanc'd as much above my expectation as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert; And moreover had aſſurance that his <hi>Royal</hi> Bounty and Goodneſs ſtill deſign'd to have done greater things for me: For how ſtrange ſoever it may appear to thoſe who know my unworthineſs of ſo high an Honour, yet in a grateful Recognition of my Obligations, I will tell the truth, in declaring that I ſtood regiſtred in his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Decrees to have ſucceeded my <hi>Lord Phaulkon</hi> in the prime Miniſtry of the Affairs of the Kingdom. But yet all this that relates to my particular Misfortunes, is not worthy of a Thought, when I reflect how much the Dignity of <hi>Our Sovereign Lord</hi> the <hi>King</hi> has ſuffer'd, and what irreparable prejudice has been done to the Honour and Intereſt of the <hi>Nation,</hi> by thoſe ſtrange meaſures have been lately taken in reſpect to <hi>Syam,</hi> and ſome other parts of <hi>India,</hi> which have not only ruin'd me and ſeveral others in our Eſtates, but deſtroy'd the Lives of many of his <hi>Majeſties</hi> uſeful Subjects. And theſe are yet but the beginnings of our Sorrows, for the ill Effects of our new Enterprizes, will be felt by Poſterity in an entire Loſs of that noble and beneficial Commerce, unleſs ſome ſpeedy and effectual Courſe be taken to retrieve and preſerve it, which I hope will be accordingly conſidered by <hi>HIM</hi> or Them, who have been the occaſion of what I have here related of the Blood-ſhed and Miſery of their poor diſtreſſed Countrymen at <hi>Mergen;</hi> For the guilt thereof is much more imputable to them than the <hi>Syamers,</hi> who in regard to the Provocations and Apprehenſions they were under, are in great meaſure excuſable. For not to ſay any thing here of the grounds of our Companies quarrel with <hi>Syam,</hi> or their ſtrange manner of proſecuting it. I am now only to take notice of this particular Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, which happening in that Place where I had ſo great a ſhare in the Government, and conſequently a Power to diſpoſe matters according to my Inclinations; In the firſt place my being an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough at that Juncture to make the Natives ſomething jealous of me: And then the reſpect that I paid to the Authority of <hi>Our Sovereign Lord</hi> the <hi>King</hi> in my friendly Reception of the Captain who had his Commiſſion, with my dutiful Obedience to his <hi>Boyal</hi> Command in diſmiſſing all my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106340:4"/>
               <hi>Countrymen</hi> from the <hi>King of Syam</hi>'s Service, might very reaſonably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their ſuſpicions. Nor was it a ſmall inducement to their further doubts, that the Company were pleas'd to employ ſo deſpicable a Force for ſo conſiderable an Attempt, which might juſtly incline them to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume there was ſome dependence on my ſelf and thoſe under my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. For to ſend no more than one little Ship of 100 Tuns, and a Sloop of 30 Tuns, with a few <hi>Europeans</hi> on them both, and to deſign ſo great a Work with this little Armado, as to block up the <hi>Port,</hi> and take all the Ships, was ſo prodigious an Exploit, that it aſtoniſh'd the <hi>Syamers,</hi> and will, I believe, cauſe great admiration in others. To which I muſt add, that the <hi>Moors, Portuguezes,</hi> and a few <hi>Dutch</hi> that reſided there, who were always very envious of our flouriſhing ſettlement at that Place, could not poſſibly have wiſh'd for a fitter opportunity to undermine our <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt;</hi> and I am very certain they did induſtriouſly improve it, in repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and aggravating every thing to our greateſt diſadvantage. But yet after all, I am well aſſur'd the <hi>Syamers,</hi> could never have been tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to that bloody Fury, had not theſe unhappy Actions of Captain <hi>Welt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> confirm'd their former Fears, and put them upon doing that Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to ſecure themſelves from the <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> they concluded was form'd againſt them by all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at that Place. Nor muſt I omit to intimate, that the Captain did afterwards, with great concern and trouble, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge he was ſenſible of his unhappy Inadvertencies, declaring he had been betray'd by the falſe Suggeſtions and evil Advice of ſome treacherous Perſons he too much confided in.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>ANd here at the cloſe I beg leave to add a Word or two in Reflection on that falſe and ſcandalous News was put into the <hi>Gazette</hi> the 26th of <hi>July</hi> paſt, the Words are theſe, <hi>The Letters likewiſe add, that at</hi> Tenaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>and</hi> Mergy, <hi>belonging to the</hi> King <hi>of</hi> Syam, <hi>the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Fugitives, and Relicts of the late Interloping Faction that fled to</hi> Phaulkon<hi>'s aſſiſtance, and were employed by him in the</hi> King <hi>of</hi> Syam<hi>'s Service, being fifty ſeven Perſons were all cut off by an Inſurrection of</hi> 600 <hi>of the Natives, with their Governor</hi> Burneby, <hi>a treacherous Deſerter from the Companies Service, ſuppoſed to have been corrupted by</hi> Phaulkon <hi>when</hi> Burneby <hi>was Chief for the</hi> Company <hi>at</hi> Syam, <hi>none eſcaped with Life, but Mr.</hi> White, Governour <hi>of</hi> Mergen <hi>for the</hi> King <hi>of</hi> Syam, <hi>and he by ſwimming off to a ſmall Ship of the</hi> Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies <hi>riding near</hi> Mergy, <hi>that ſaved and relieved him, notwithſtanding his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer miſcarriages, by giving him a ſmall Prize Ship in which he ſailed for, and arrived at the Cape, and (it is thought) will come from thence to</hi> Europe <hi>in ſome of the</hi> Dutch Eaſt-India <hi>Ships, the ſmall Ship being not fitted for a</hi> Europe <hi>Voyage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Paragraph, and 'tis really great pity the Authors Name was not affix'd to it, whereby we might know who he is amongſt Mankind that dares with ſuch audacious effrontery impoſe on the Publick. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not readily imagine what ſhould tempt any Man to ſuch a Crime, unleſs it be ſome body who is conſcious to himſelf, he has been the fundamental occaſion of all that Blood and Ruine at <hi>Mergen,</hi> and now hopes by this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnious Forgery to cover his Guilt from the cognizance of the World. And certainly it muſt be ſome ſuch Perſon that fram'd this Story, wherein there is not the leaſt ſemblance of Truth, ſaving that he has hit about the number of them that were ſlain: but then to wound their Names after they had ſo unhappily loſt their Lives, in a moſt falſe and groundleſs accuſing them
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106340:5"/>to have been <hi>Interlopers</hi> and <hi>Fugitives,</hi> ſpeaks the Author to have more of the Cruelty of a <hi>Canibal</hi> than the Charity of a Chriſtian. For firſt, I dare affirm to the Author's face, and can teſtifie to the World, that near one third of them that fell, were the very Men that came on the <hi>Curtana</hi> to fight the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies Battels, and amongſt all the reſt, there was no more than one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Perſon that came out in an Interloping Ship, the others being generally ſuch as had reſided ſome years in the Country, and ſeveral of them came the preceding year from <hi>Madraſs</hi> by leave of the <hi>Preſident</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> to ſerve the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Syam</hi> in his Wars with <hi>Golcondah</hi> and <hi>Pegu.</hi> But I obſerve our Author doth in this malicious miſrepreſentation, ſpit his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom more directly at that unfortunate Man Mr. <hi>Richard Burneby,</hi> whom he brands with the black Character of a <hi>Treacherous Deſerter,</hi> which is ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious a Slander, that any modeſt Man alive, but our Author, would be aſham'd ſo baſely to traduce a poor dead Man, and add new Grief to the affliction of his diſtreſſed Widow and Fatherleſs Children. For Mr. <hi>Burneby</hi>'s Caſe was in one Word this; He ſerv'd the Company in place of their Chief at the Factory of <hi>Syam</hi> about two years, and Mr. <hi>George Goſsfright</hi> coming thither as Superviſor from the Agency, <hi>Anno</hi> 81. he found ſome faults in his Management; (which by the way I muſt do him right, to declare, were at worſt but Errors in his Judgment, not his Will) but however he was diſplac'd, and went with Mr. <hi>Goſsfright</hi> to <hi>Bantam,</hi> where he was diſcharg'd from the Companies Service by the Council, that then managed their Affairs, and after ſome Months ſtay there, and at <hi>Batavia,</hi> he did with their leave return on a <hi>Dutch</hi> Ship to <hi>Syam.</hi> And as to that ingrateful inſinuation of his being corrupted by <hi>Phaulkon,</hi> all I will now ſay of it, is, That it is like the many other returns have been made to that <hi>Honourable Perſon</hi> my <hi>Lord Phaulkon,</hi> for his great Favours to the Nation in general, and ſeveral of <hi>Our Countrymen</hi> in particular.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude, As to thoſe Suggeſtions concerning my ſelf, <hi>That I ſaved my Life by ſwimming aboard one of the Companies Ships, and their Servants did not only relieve me, but nottwithſtanding my former Miſcarriages were ſo kind to give me a ſmall Prize, on which I arrived at the Cape.</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to the true account I have given in this Paper of all that paſs'd in thoſe Extremities, for a full Confutation of theſe Fictions, and will only add; That when I am accus'd of my pretended Miſcarriages, I will render any reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſatisfaction for whatever can be prov'd againſt me, as I alſo preſume to expect the Company will at length be pleas'd to give me thanks at leaſt for thoſe good Services they already know I have done them. But if after all, it be impoſſible to merit ſo much favour at their hands; <hi>how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,</hi> ſince God has in great Mercy been pleas'd, after I have paſt through ſo many Dangers and Miſeries, to bring me home alive on a Ship of my own, to which I have as good a Title as the Author can pretend to any thing he poſſeſſes in the World; I hope, that when I have recover'd that conſiderable Eſtate which the Companies Servants have with moſt inhumane Violence taken from me, and obtain'd ſatisfaction for thoſe vaſt Loſſes and Injuries I ſuſtain'd by their Hoſtile Attempts at <hi>Mergen;</hi> I ſhall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abl'd to provide my ſelf with Ships, and all things elſe that my Occaſions require, without being beholden to the Author or his Accomplices.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Samuel White.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
